So here is a value iteration theorem can read
all of it I apologize I go can't go down my
hand writing seriously detoriates at which
this condition in 3 is met for all N greater
than capital in okay so pi defined by step
four is epsilon optimal and v n plus one minus
v star is less than or equal to epsilon by
2 when 3 holds so when this holds v n plus
one is epsilon by 2 close to v star right
so what is it A and B of kind of easy we already
seen that A and B as essentially Banach's
fixed point theorem right.
I am sorry yeah the Banach fixed point theorem
gives us A and B correct what is the difference
between C and D why do I have two of these
things so they look contradict they look contradictory
not order it per say but we did not anyone
gives me the right answer I will give you
a bonus mark that essentially which have been
following whatever I have been saying so far
so further we will have to take down the roll
number and note down that now I got their
attention to people who do not know the class
averages for my wishes tend to be in like
2 or 3 out of 20 or 50 it does not matter
what the denominator is does not seemed to
change but so every mark matters so tell me
what is the difference why do I need C and
D sorry this ? optimal means it is if you
say it in a different way then you will get
it so what I am saying is that v pi minus
v star is less than ? here I am saying v n
plus minus v star is less than epsilon by
two .
Remember my space V does not necessarily contain
only value functions it is just a space of
functions right v n plus one need not be the
value function corresponding to the policy
pi even though I recover pi by being greedy
with respect to v n plus 1 does not mean if
I actually solve for value of pi if I find
V pi it need not be v n plus 1 right so what
three is telling me is that v pi is epsilon
not what C is telling me is v pi epsilon optimal
what D is telling me is that v n plus 1 epsilon
by 2 optimal okay so fun let me give you the
work how about you enough I never offered
them before right.
This is this is on offer nobody took it that
is easy enough right all you need to do is
just mean following the multiple times I kept
saying that V is not the space of value function
is the very beginning when somebody said V
is a space of value function I corrected you
of this class very beginning of this class
anyway so let us look at the proof well A
and B are immediate the follower banach fixed
point theorem so we will start off with C
and D right so just assume that 3 is made
for some n okay so n it is already met that
condition has been met right and that V p
the p has been derived from doing this the
p has been derived from doing this.
And now I can use my triangle inequality right
it does not matter that then this actually
does not matter right whether these conditions
are met or not I can take an arbitrary v pi
and a V star and I can use a triangle inequality
and write this because it is just about three
points in space right we talked about how
I can keep using the triangle inequality in
an arbitrary fashion because all I am talking
about are just some 3 points in space it so
happens that one of them is V pi other one
is V n plus 1 the third one is v star but
this will hold regardless of which three points
I pick okay.
So here is a tricky thing I want you to look
at
so let us look at L pi say I want Lpi to act
on V n plus 1 right I want Lpi to act on v
n plus 1 right so what will be Lpi acting
on Vn plus 1 is it space of what Lpi is a
an operator corresponding to the bellman equation
for pi right sort of way I said last class
we left off by saying l pi is a contraction
so that Lpi so Lpiis just a bellman value
equation operating on Vn plus 1 so what would
that be will be this right this but instead
of argmax here I will have a summation over
p Sa say a summation over pi Sa but what I
have done here by pi itself is an argmax a
right just one action.
So if you remember I told you about the deterministic
policy is right so this whole thing will go
I will just replace this with pi of s is this
will be expected value of R given S, pi of
s probability of s' given s,pi of s v n plus
1 of s dash so that will essentially be the
Lpi acting on v n plus 1 right is it clear
this is L pi on v n plus 1 I just read it
out I just write in unit known as mnemonic
expected value of R given s, pi of s + gamma
times summation over s' probability of s'
given pi of s x v n plus 1 s' okay so now
thing that you have to notice how would I
get to this pi of s is by using max I use
the max operator over this right.
So if I had done L on v n plus 1 what would
I have obtained L on Vn plus 1 is essentially
this right nice right this is this is what
this one L or Vn plus 1is essentially this
right so what I have done here because I chose
my pi to be the max action here so whether
I apply Lpi on Vn plus 1 or whether I apply
L on Vn plus 1 it is the same because the
p was chosen to be the max action right so
I can say that this is equal to sorry so the
two are equal
that makes it easier.
(Refer Slide Time: 12:24)
Now we are going to start simplifying stuff.
(Refer Slide Time: 12:27)
So I am going to take this expression I am
going to try and simplify that
okay we can I can replace v pi with ?^?l pi
v pi done right v pi is a fixed point nothing
will change I can just replace it to the Lpi
now
so can I do this same application of the triangle
inequality as we had before so three points
are L pi v pi, Vn plus 1 and LVn plus 1 so
LVn plus 1 is just another point in space
between three points I can write this triangle
inequality so this is less than or equal to
H this is equal to
right so this is the reduction we talked about
here so from LV I went to L?_p? LV n plus
1 I wen L pi v n plus 1 and from v n plus
1 I went to L V nbecause that is how Vn plus
1 was generated by applying L on VL okay so
I have written that.
(Refer Slide Time: 15:06)
Now I can simplify this
so I have V pi n plus 1here v pi minus v n
plus 1 here sorry and v pi minus v n plus
1here so I can take it to that side simplify
things so I will just get okay that is just
the first term now we have to simplify the
second term what is the second term.
(Refer Slide Time: 16:07)
I just like we did earlier I have done a repeated
application of the triangle inequality is
only tricky thing here is a summation goes
to infinity because only when I repeat this
till infinity will go to v star right but
that is fine because this is anyway it is
a vanishing quantity as we go along right
so this of this sum will actually okay exist
limit of a summation yeah well I am you can
think of this as V star minus v n plus 1 right
because I am just talking about the norm right
so as V star minus v n plus 1 and then I have
written this up okay.
So this is v n plus 1 that is v n plus 2then
v n plus 2 v n plus 3 blah this one so forth
so what will this be you only said it to be
a limit of a summation right guys I need to
take 1 gamma out okay so what do we have so
we have the first component is less than equal
to
norm of v square minus v n plus 1less then
equal to gamma upon 1 minus gamma intonorm
of v n plus 1 minus v n right but when 3 holds
what is v n plus 1 minus v n 1 minus gamma
upon 2 gamma right so if I plug that then
what will I get epsilon by 2 to plug it in
there what will I get epsilon by 2 so I have
few components here so v pi minus v star is
less than or equal to epsilon by plus epsilon
by 2 which is epsilon right v pi minus v star
is less than or equal to okay when we have
actually to complete the proof we have to
do that but I am asking you to do that what
was the other thing that we wanted to show
D or later right.
So D essentially was to show that v n plus
1will be at least epsilon by 2 close so we
already done so we substitute that here so
we get epsilon by 2 so is that so VN - sorry
v n plus minus v star is less than or equal
to epsilon by 2and what we are showing there
is v pi minus v star is less than or equal
to epsilon like so that is basically done
so we have shown this theorem so essentially
what we have here is that value iteration
converges with that stopping criterion it
converges to a epsilon optimal policy so you
have to pick an epsioln first remember gamma
comes as part of the problem definition.
So once you pick an epsilon you can find a
stopping criterion using that expression there
and you are all set okay so there is one other
very interesting thing that people talk about
from a theoretical analysis of algorithms
for solving these kinds of MDPs right so it
is called the rate of convergence so I have
shown you that it converges so there is a
whole concept called rate of convergence right
how quickly does it approached right so I
am not going to get into a huge discussions
on rate of convergence and like I mentioned
with the deterministic policy thing I actually
put up a small right upon rate of convergence
as well you can read it.
One thing which I want to tell you is that
so you can with a little bit of not much right
so L is a contraction mapping L is a contraction
so at every iteration right so my
so what is the contraction factor for L we
did this gamma right so for every iteration
I can show that my iterates that is basically
I start off with v0 then I become take me
one then V2 V3 and so on so forth every iteration
I can so that the successive iterates will
become gamma closer to v star right.
So I have some so v1 was some x close to v
star then v2 will be gamma X closer to so
gamma is small it will converge faster if
gamam is very large it will converse lower
right so this is called linear convergence
with the rate of gamam right so if it falls
as gamma square then it will be quadratic
convergence right so but linear convergence
with the rate of gamam so this is essentially
the thing so the interesting aspects I mean
if you want to get into the more into the
theory of all of these things is to start
studying the rates of convergence of different
algorithms and so on so forth which I am not
going to get into but there is something for
as an aside so that you can look at it.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resource Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights Reserved